Finding Aid for the Lucile, Lady Duff-Gordon Drawings LSC.0624
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lucile, Lady Duff-Gordon drawings
1913-1923
1913-1917
UCLA Library Special Collections
Duff Gordon, Lucy, Lady
LSC.0624
255 items (25 oversize boxes)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Existence and Location of Copies note for the link to the digitized materials.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9951651533606533
Biography
Lucile, Lady Duff-Gordon, was born Lucy Christiana Sutherland in London in 1863. She began a dressmaking business after her divorce from James Stuart Wallace. The business was successful and evolved into Maison Lucile, a couture house known for Lucile's ethereal and colorful designs, as well as for its celebrity clientele. In 1900 she married Sir Cosmo Duff-Gordon. In addition to her couture house, she wrote fashion columns for the Hearst papers as well as fashion magazines. Some of the commissions she worked on around the time of these sketches were for the British premiere of the Franz Lehar operetta, The merry widow (1907), for Broadway's Ziegfeld follies revues (1915-1921), and for the Hollywood film, Way down East (1920). She died on April 20, 1935, at the age of 71, of breast cancer at a nursing home in London.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of fashion sketches by Lucile, Lady Duff-Gordon. The color sketches are in pen or pencil with descriptions.
Organization and Arrangement
Sketches are arranged chronologically, 1913-1923, with the exception of some material added later, which date from 1916-1917 and appear at the end.
General note
Note: For identification purposes, please use the UCLA drawing number penciled on the verso in the lower left corner.
Costume design drawings; Women fashion designers -- England -- Archives.; Duff Gordon, Lucy, Lady--Archives.
- 2/14, pencil sketch of back view in upper right-hand corner, Lucile signature. [Two piece crème colored military style dress with black hat and walking stick]., 1913; UCLA Drawing No. 1; Foxing in upper middle area, pencil smudging on bottom. (Box 1)
- 2/1, pencil sketch of back view in upper right-hand corner, Lucile signature. [One-piece crème colored military style dress with black hat], 1913; UCLA Drawing No. 2; Slight smudging on top and bottom. (Box 1)
- 2/16, Lucile signature. [Yellow-striped two-piece dress over a white collared shirt with a black tie]., 1913; UCLA Drawing No. 3; Foxing on left-hand middle area, smudging on all 4 sides and in middle area, "No. 5" faintly written on upper right-hand corner. (Box 1)
- 2/17, pencil sketch of back view in upper right-hand corner, Lucile signature. [Collared blue-grey dress with buttons along the sleeves and a veiled hat]., 1913; UCLA Drawing No. 4; Foxing on bottom left-hand corner, smudging on upper left-hand corner and bottom, "No. 3" faintly written on lower left-hand corner. (Box 1)
- 2/18, pencil sketch of back view in upper right-hand corner and of front view in lower left-hand corner, Lucile signature. [Blue jacket and skirt w/purple sash and white buttoned shirt w/purple tasseled hat]., 1913; UCLA Drawing No. 5; Smudging on all 4 sides and around upper right-hand sketch, faint illegible writing on lower left-hand corner. (Box 1)
- 2/19, pen sketch of back view in upper right-hand corner, Lucile signature. [Layered camel-colored dress w/white collared shirt underneath with black and white tie and a white feathered hat]., 1913; UCLA Drawing No. 6; Foxing on upper right-hand corner and middle bottom, smudging on bottom (Box 1)
- 1, pen sketch of back view in lower right-hand corner. "Rose and White Striped Pussy Willow Dress with Frills of White Lace. Model #34 - 'Sally'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 7 (Box 1)
- 2, colored sketch of back view in lower left-hand corner. "Black Pussy Willow with Check Border Gown, Model #25 - 'Check Mate'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 8; Slight tear on lower left hand side, slight smudging on lower left-hand corner. (Box 1)
- 3, colored sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Dry those Tears, Model #33". [Grey colored dress with white collars and black and white checkered hems on sleeves and waist along w/black & white ribbon around neck]., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 9; Foxing on bottom middle and right-hand middle side, smudging on bottom left-hand corner. (Box 1)
- 4, pen sketch of back view on left-hand corner, "'The Gardeners Daughter', gown Model #32". [Blue plaid and lime colored apron styled dress with open collar and green hat], 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 10; Foxing on bottom middle, smudging on bottom and right-hand middle. (Box 1)
- 5, colored sketch of back view, "Blue and white spot pussy willow gown Model #30 - 'Fifty fifty'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 11; Foxing on lower right side edge. (Box 2)
- 6, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Ecru lace with black lace net border with pink sash and binding Model #41 - 'Araminta'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 12; Slight foxing on middle bottom, thumbprint on lower middle. (Box 2)
- 7, colored sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Pale rose tulle and pearls embroidered restaurant gown Model #57 - 'Kolokoltchik'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 13; Foxing on bottom edge and lower left-hand corner. (Box 2)
- 8, colored sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Printed Kensington tussore afternoon gown with green taffeta coat Model #31 - 'The Only Wa'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 14; Smudge on lower right-hand corner. (Box 2)
- 9, pen sketch on back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Black silk three piece suit Model #8 - 'Saros'"., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 15; Foxing on upper right edge. (Box 2)
- 10, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, two pen sketches of the skirt on lower right-hand corner, "White Tussore suit Model #18 - 'The Unknown'"., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 16; Stains on middle right-hand side and lower left-hand corner, foxing in the middle, smudging on all four sides. (Box 2)
- 11, colored sketch of back view on lower right-hand side, "Old rose silk three piece suit (dress) Model #1 - 'Sourain Dere'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 17; Foxing in upper left-hand corner and lower right-hand corner. (Box 2)
- 12, pen sketch on bottom right-hand corner, "White cloth three piece suit, fancy leather belt, black velvet collar and cuffs Model #5 - 'The Magnet'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 18; Foxing on lower left-hand corner and upper left-hand corner. (Box 2)
- 13, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Black silk three piece suit with black and white striped waist Model #8 - 'Saros'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 19; Foxing along bottom edge. (Box 2)
- 14, colored sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Pale grey violet gown trimmed with satin Model #11 - 'Grey Cloud'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 20; Foxing on bottom right-hand corner and top middle, tear on bottom left-hand corner, dried water spot on lower left-hand corner. (Box 2)
- 15, pen sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Black Marquisette and White Broid afternoon gown Model #23 - 'Parted'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 21; Foxing on lower right-hand edge, smudging in middle right-hand side. (Box 3)
- 16, colored sketch on bottom left-hand corner, "Dark blue silk with large white flower afternoon gown Model #24 - 'Why Wa'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 22; Foxing on lower left-hand side, faint illegible writing on upper right-hand corner, bent on bottom left-hand side. (Box 3)
- 17, pen sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "White cloth afternoon gown trimmed with buttons and white silk broid Model #26 - 'Gertie'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 23; Foxing on upper middle. (Box 3)
- 18, colored sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "White muslin embroidered in black gown, mauve cape Model #39 - 'Petite Histoire'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 24; Foxing on upper right-hand side, water spot on lower left-hand corner, slight tear on upper left-hand corner. (Box 3)
- 19, pen sketch on lower left-hand corner, "Blue shot taffeta afternoon dress with deep cream embroidered chiffon apron Model #28 - 'Time Was'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 25; Foxing on middle left-hand edge and on right-hand side, red colored mark on upper right-hand corner. (Box 3)
- 20, pen sketch of back view on upper right-hand corner, "Green and gold theatre dress Model #62 - 'Carnival'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 26; Foxing on upper right-hand corner, smudges on the corners. (Box 3)
- 21, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Black satin race coat, lined Myson silk Model #70 - 'Lafitte'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 27; Colored pink spots on bottom, discoloration on right-hand corner. (Box 3)
- 22, colored sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Dark blue gabardine race coat Model #71 - 'Doncastir'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 28; Foxing on bottom left-hand corner, tear on bottom left-hand side, smudging on bottom, middle left-hand side, and upper right-hand corner, water spot on lower right-hand side. (Box 3)
- 23, pen sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Yellow lace and pink chiffon tea gown Model #72 - 'Doragaia'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 29; Bent upper right-hand corner, smudge on upper and lower right-hand side. (Box 3)
- 24, colored sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Blue short messaline evening coat Model #65 - 'Flavia'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 30; Bent upper left-hand corner, smudging on bottom left and bottom right-hand corner. (Box 3)
- 25, colored sketch of back view of bottom left-hand corner, "Rose broche evening coat Model #66 - 'Sans Gene'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 31; Colored spots on bottom left-hand corner and upper right edge. (Box 4)
- 26, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Cream lace dress, belt and long ends of a warm gray chameuece Model #73 - 'Hiloise'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 32; Foxing on upper right-hand edge, bent upper left-hand corner, smudge on lower right-hand side and middle left edge. (Box 4)
- 27, colored sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Pervanche blue chiffon and charmeuese tea gown. Coat of blue silk net embroidered in silver Model #67 - 'Douckka'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 33; Fon bottom right-hand corner and top middle edge, bent upper left and right-hand corners. (Box 4)
- 28, colored sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "White muslin embroidered black gown Model #39 - 'Petite Histoire'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 34; Foxing on bottom right-hand corner, bent on bottom left edge. (Box 4)
- 29, colored sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Pale blue organdre gown Model #38 - 'Rive D' Ete'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 35; Foxing on upper left-hand edge and bottom edge, bent on bottom left-hand corner, black spot on upper right-hand corner. (Box 4)
- 30, colored sketch of back view on bottom left-hand corner, "Pale green taffeta and lace afternoon gown Model #35 - 'Wesnia'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 36; Smudge on upper left-hand edge, "No. 35" faintly written on upper right-hand corner. (Box 4)
- 31, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Fawn and flowered fancy crepe afternoon dress Model #29 - 'Remember Me'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 37; Foxing on upper right-hand corner, smudges on top and bottom, pen scribble on upper right-hand corner. (Box 4)
- 32, pen sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Leaf green tulle ball dress with gold lace Model #46 - 'Obstination'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 38; Foxing on left-hand side and middle right-hand side. (Box 4)
- 33, colored sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Rose taffeta and net ball dress Model #44 - 'Porte Bonheur'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 39; Foxing on right-hand edge and bottom, bent bottom left-hand corner. (Box 4)
- 34, colored sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Silver tulle and lace dinner gown Model #42 - 'Lady Blessington'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 40; Foxing on right-hand side and upper left-hand side, bent upper left and right corners and bottom left corner, grease spot on lower left-hand side. (Box 4)
- 35, pen sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "White indestructible voile gown, bindings of pussy willow Model #40 - 'I'm Lonesome'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 41; Foxing on upper right-hand corner and lower right-hand side, smudging on upper left-hand corner, bent upper left-hand corner. (Box 5)
- 36, pen sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Blue and black brocade and spangled tulle evening gown Model #49 - 'Dear Lady Disdain'"., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 42; Smudge on upper right-hand side. (Box 5)
- 37, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand side, "Nattier blue and spangled embroidered gown Model #48 - 'Aurora'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 43; Foxing on right-hand edge and upper right-hand corner. (Box 5)
- 38, colored sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, "Petunia tulle and silver evening gown Model #51 - 'Foolish One'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 44; Tear on upper right-hand side, smudges on upper right and bottom, "51" written faintly on upper left-hand corner, grease spot on bottom left and upper right-hand corner. (Box 5)
- 39, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Louie XV ball gown of faded rose taffeta, bodice of orange satin-festivious of silver lace Model #50 - 'A Dedication'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 45; Foxing on bottom and upper right-hand corner, bent upper right-hand corner. (Box 5)
- 40, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Peach satin and tulle ball gown with wreath of brilliant colored flowers, Model #56 - 'Esmi'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 46; Foxing on upper right and left-hand corners and bottom right-hand corner, bent upper right-hand corner, smudging on bottom edge. (Box 5)
- 41, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "White embroidered satin and tulle evening gown, Model #5 - 'For Somebody's Darling'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 47; Foxing on top edge, smudges on top and bottom. (Box 5)
- 42, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Pale blue embroidered satin evening gown with super blue tulle drapery, Model #52 - 'Mia Cara'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 48; Foxing on middle right-hand side, smudges on upper left and right-hand corners and lower left-hand corner, bent upper right-hand corner. (Box 5)
- 43, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Scarlett chiffon and silver lace evening gown, Model #60 - 'Visharmvan'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 49; Foxing upper left and right-hand corners, smudging on top and bottom. (Box 5)
- 44, colored sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Purple chiffon evening coat, Model #59 - 'Krasavitza"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 50; Foxing on right-hand side and upper left-hand corner, "64" faintly written on upper right-hand corner. (Box 5)
- 45, colored sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Turquoise tulle restaurant gown with pale green bindings, Model #58 - 'Why Do You Hesitate?'", 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 51; Foxing on left side and upper right-hand corner and lower right-hand corner. (Box 6)
- 46, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Black jet and tulle evening gown, Model #61- 'Boyarinia'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 52; Foxing on bottom middle, grease spots on middle left and right-hand sides, smudges on upper left and right and bottom right-hand corners. (Box 6)
- 47, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand, "Petunia chiffon evening cloak trimmed with gold lace, Model #64 - 'Arunodaya'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 53; Foxing on upper and lower right-hand corners, smudge on lower left-hand corner, bent upper left-hand corner. (Box 6)
- 48, pencil sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Green striped evening cloak of taffeta, Model #63 - 'Boubentchik'"., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 54; Foxing on upper right-hand corner and middle right-hand side, smudges on bottom, paint spots on upper middle area. (Box 6)
- 49, colored sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Black lace and grey tulle restaurant gown, Model #75 - 'Chez Vous'"., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 55; Foxing on middle left-hand side and upper middle area, smudge on upper right-hand corner. (Box 6)
- 50, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "White chiffon embroidered grey gown with a grey satin belt, Model #77 - 'A Forgetting'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 56; Foxing on right-hand and bottom edges. (Box 6)
- 51, colored sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "White lace gown with bindings and belt of pale blue satin, Model #76 - 'Potzalue'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 57; Foxing on bottom and lower right-hand edges, smudge on upper left-hand corner, water spot on middle right-hand edge. (Box 6)
- 52, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "White organdic afternoon gown embroidered in pink beet and bindings of pink charmeuse, Model #79 - 'Olivia'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 58; Foxing on upper middle area and lower left-hand corner, bent lower left-hand corner. (Box 6)
- 53, colored sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, "Cream embroidered muslin dress with bindings and bows of pale blue, Model #80 - 'Plitchka'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 59; Foxing along upper left-hand and middle right-hand edges, bent lower left and right-hand corners. (Box 6)
- 54, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Rose and silver tea gown, Model #78 - 'Sarogini'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 60; Foxing on right-hand and bottom edges and upper middle area, bent upper right-hand and lower left-hand corners, smudging on middle left-hand edge, water spot on middle right-hand area. (Box 6)
- 55, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "White chiffon trimmed with green gown, Model #86 - 'Baby Mine'"., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 61; Foxing on upper left and right-hand corners and middle left-hand side, smudge on lower left-hand corner. (Box 7)
- 56, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "Grey and silver brocade evening gown and grey net, Model #84 - 'Yasodhara'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 62; Foxing on middle right-hand area and left-hand corner, water spot on middle right-hand side, smudge on lower right-hand edge. (Box 7)
- 57, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "White satin dinner dress, Model #83 - 'For Ever'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 63; Foxing on lower right-hand corner and middle right-hand side, smudging on upper and lower left-hand corners, grease spot on upper middle area. (Box 7)
- 58, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, "White voile dress with bindings of pussy willow, Model #81 - 'My Love'"., 1915/Spring; UCLA Drawing No. 64; Foxing on lower left-hand and upper and lower right-hand edges and lower-middle area, smudging on bottom left and right- hand corners, bent upper right-hand corner. (Box 7)
- 59, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [white collared tan colored dress with belt and veiled hat]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 65; Foxing on upper and lower left-hand edges, smudging on all 4 sides, discoloration on dress. (Box 7)
- 60, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [grey belted two-piece dress suit with long veiled hat]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 66; Foxing on upper left-hand and lower right-hand corners, water spot on upper right-hand corner. (Box 7)
- 61, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [rose printed black skirt with fur trimmed cape and green and blue bows]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 67; Foxing on top and bottom edges, smudging on bottom edge. (Box 7)
- 62, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [grey black high-collared fur coat with matching fur cap]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 68; Foxing on left-hand side, smudging on upper left-hand corner, faint illegible writing on upper right-hand corner, water spots on middle right-hand area. (Box 7)
- 63, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, [white collared purple dress with sash and fur trim along the sleeves and black hat]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 69; Foxing on upper right-hand area, smudges on upper and lower areas, indentation in upper left-hand area. (Box 7)
- 64, pen sketch of back view on bottom right-hand corner, [pale blue two-piece dress trimmed with white lace and matching pale blue hat]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 70; Smudges on all four corners, slightly wrinkled in upper left and right-hand corners. (Box 7)
- 65, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, [pale blue skirt with blue sash and frilly white blouse with pale blue hat]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 71; Faint illegible writing on top middle area, smudge on bottom edge. (Box 8)
- 66, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [tan chevron patterned two-piece dress suit and a hat with a black bow and walking stick]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 72; Minor foxing on all 4 sides, smudges along all 4 sides, "No. 2" written in ink on upper left-hand corner. (Box 8)
- 67, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [ blue-grey two-piece dress with striped designs along the sleeves and sides with green tassels in front and purple hat with circular attachment]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 73; Foxing on upper edge and lower left-hand corner, smudging on lower right-hand area. (Box 8)
- 68, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [grey dress with big pockets and buttons lining the front and transparent sleeves]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 74; Foxing on dress, blue smudge on bottom left-hand corner. (Box 8)
- 69, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [blue-grey layered skirt with pale blue spotted jacket with green and purple and pink bindings along the edges and green tassels in front]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 75; Foxing on bottom left and right-hand corners, smudging on left side. (Box 8)
- 70, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [blue-grey two-piece dress suit with a high magenta collar with magenta buttons and yellow hat]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 76; Foxing on left-hand edge and upper right-hand corner. (Box 8)
- 71, colored sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [gold-printed lace skirt with pink and black rose printed drapery with fur trimmings and pink and green sashes and mink and flowered straps]., [no date]; UCLA Drawing No. 77; Foxing on upper and lower left-hand corners, blue smudges on upper right-hand corner. (Box 8)
- 72, pen sketch of back view on lower right-hand corner, [layered fur and plum colored dress with fur trimmings and yellow cascading hat]., 1915/Autumn; UCLA Drawing No. 78; Foxing on upper left and lower right-hand corners. (Box 8)
- 73, pen sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, [fur-trimmed negligee-like dress with silver printed flowers and a black sash]., 1915/Autumn; UCLA Drawing No. 79; Foxing on right side and lower left-hand corner, smudging on lower right-hand corner, bent upper and lower left-hand corners. (Box 8)
- 74, colored sketch of back view on lower left-hand corner, [lime green, turquoise, and black layered off-the-shoulder dress]., 1915/Autumn; UCLA Drawing No. 80; Foxing along left-hand edge, smudging on right side. (Box 8)